[Music]
so
hello everybody welcome to the 32nd
live episode of the ask a budget show
and as you know today we discuss science
which for me is
physics and mathematics and
astrophysics and computer science
artificial intelligence all that it is
not sociology it is not
political science it is not the social
sciences etc
so that's what we discussed today let me
take a look at who all is here with us
today
hello kishore thank you moshmi
hi prasham hi ram kurya
hello simpo hello koka prasham shah
hello
hi harshada
and everybody else i'm unfortunately
unable to take everyone's name but
good evening and good day to all of you
it's great to see you all here
so let's get into the questions straight
away because that's what we do
let's start with question one
okay question one is by cha hat
so chahat says that galaxies looks
stationary so
so why do scientists say that they
rotate
that's a very good question so according
to what we know about galaxies or
according to what scientists say about
galaxies
a galaxy a typical galaxy like the milky
way for example would
complete one full rotation in about a
billion years or so maybe some are
faster maybe some are slower but
something like that right
so that's a very slow rate of rotation
so how do we know that galaxies are
rotating that's a
very good question i'm sure your
teachers never answered this question
i'm sure that you did not even get to
ask this question because you can't ask
questions in school
so how do we know that galaxies rotate
there is something
in physics called redshift and blueshift
you must have heard of the doppler
effect the doppler effect is when you
are standing stationary
and the train is coming towards you at a
high speed and the trains
whistle or siren seems shrill
when the train is coming towards you but
the moment it passes you
the pitch of the whistle changes it
becomes lower in pitch
so that's an example of the doppler
effect because when the train is coming
towards you
the frequency of the waves is compressed
uh the wavelengths are compressed and
that's why the sound seems
higher and when the train is receding
away from you
that's when the wavelengths of the sound
are elongated and that's why it sounds
uh lower in frequency
so the same thing happens with light so
there is
a doppler effect in light as well
there's red shift and blue shift when
light when a luminous object is receding
away from you
it's light waves it's it's uh the the
wavelength of the light is elongated
and that's why it appears redder than
whether than if it was not moving away
from you
and if it's coming towards you then the
light is blue shifted towards the blue
end of the spectrum because the
uh wavelengths are compressed so there's
redshift in this blue shift
so if you look at a galaxy if you
observe one end
then you will find that the light is red
shifted so for example you have certain
spectral lines
for example sodium sodium and other
other elements that produce
very specific light they produce light
of very specific wavelengths
and when you observe those wavelengths
from a distant galaxy
you will find that at one of one end of
the galaxy those wavelengths are red
shifted
which means that that end of the galaxy
is moving away from you
and on the other hand of the galaxy on
the other side of the galaxy you will
find that the same
wavelengths are blue shifted which means
that they are moving towards you
so the galaxy one side of the galaxy is
moving away from you
the other side of the galaxy is moving
towards you this is clear from the red
shift and blue shift that you see from
the two opposite ends of the galaxy and
that indicates
that the galaxy is rotating right so
that's one way one
one excellent way of of determining
that whether a galaxy is rotating or not
and we find that all galaxies are
rotating
and depending on various measurements we
can actually determine
to a good extent the rate at which it is
rotating how fast is it rotating
and that's how we get the galaxy
rotation curves those graphs which
actually showed us
that there is missing matter out there
and that's how dark matter came into the
picture
now how what's the other way that we
know that galaxies are rotating
well most galaxies are spiral in shape
how do you get a spiral shape let me
show you how you can get a spiral shape
let me just play a five second video for
you
hang on
so that is a ball that is wet and it's
been spun like that and you can see
the spiral shape that it's creating the
water is ejected
in a spiral shape so that's precisely
what we see in galaxies
the the video i just showed you is that
of a ball on earth
it's a very slow motion video high frame
rate
but that's the same sort of shape that
you see in galaxies
so the the spirals are at a 90 degree
angle from the axis of rotation
so that's another way that we know that
galaxies are rotating and that's how we
know for a fact based on this
observational evidence
on various different kinds of
that galaxies are indeed rotating we
know they are rotating we can actually
measure the rate of rotation even though
we can't see a galaxy
do a full a full rotation because it
would take a billion years or hundreds
of millions of years
and we don't live that long and yet
we're able to tell that they rotate
so this is how it's done good question
very good question
pink line cab cabs asks i have had this
doubt for a long time that despite
the extremely small sizes of particles
how do scientists and physicists measure
them
so what you're asking is let's say you
have an atom
or a nucleus of an atom basically
subatomic particles
so how do we know the sizes of these
so this is a question that's similar to
the rate of rotation of galaxies but
it's at the opposite an
end of that of the scale galaxies are in
immensely large subatomic particles are
immensely small
and yet we know that the the nucleus of
an atom has a certain size we know that
other sub-atomic particles
have a certain size how do we know that
that's an excellent question
did your teachers ever answer this i
doubt it very much
right so here's how it's done let's say
you
uh want to measure the
size of the nucleus of an aluminum atom
so what you do is you take a thin sheet
of aluminum you know aluminum foil right
you try and make it as
thin as possible and that is your target
and then you create a vacuum apparatus
you place the aluminum sheet as the
target
and you shoot a beam of electrons let's
say electrons you can shoot anything
but let's say you shoot a beam of
electrons
at this target and you set up detectors
behind the target and at various angles
around the target
and you see how many electrons are
scattered in what direction
so we know that atoms are mostly empty
space it's it's a nucleus and you have
electrons around that
and most of it is empty space so most of
the electrons that you shoot at the
aluminum nuclear aluminum atoms they're
just going to pass through the
aluminum foil right they're just going
to pass through them
and yet some electrons are going to get
deflected
from the nucleus at various angles and
in extremely rare cases
you will find that electrons will hit a
nucleus head on
and bounce back in the opposite
direction so that also is to be measured
so then you determine how many electrons
were fired
okay you can measure that and you can
detect how many uh
hits you were able to measure behind the
the
the target or at various angles around
the target
and on the opposite end of the target
and based on these
calculations how many uh measurements
you are able to make at what angles
you can determine the the size of the
nucleus so it involves a bit of
trigonometry
geometry algebra all that but it's it's
it's the
theory is pretty simple so that's how it
is done
so basically let's say you you shoot
one million electrons at a single uh
atom of aluminum and let's say out of
those 1 million electrons
99.3 percent just
fly away and they just pass through the
atom
but a small percentage will be deflected
right back so that percentage tells you
what percentage of the atom
is actually the nucleus so we know that
the nucleus is very small and then based
on other calculations you can determine
exactly
or or not exactly but to a good uh
fidelity
how large the atom is and what is the uh
probability of error in that what is the
error calculation in that
so that is is essentially how we
calculate or we measure the the actual
sizes of atoms and nuclei so you can do
that
do this with aluminum we can do it with
gold
we can do it with calcium and eventually
you can even do it with hydrogen and all
that right
so that is how it's done and this is a
process that takes long time
in the very beginning it was thought
that atoms are essentially like plum
puddings
you have a smeared out charge in them
and later it was discovered that they
actually have a nucleus because they
did this very same experiment and they
found that the very small percentage of
electrons actually bounce back
and that's how it was discovered that
atoms have nuclei and then
this experiment was refined and done
over time for
over the various decades and that's how
today because of the improvements in the
experimental apparatuses and all that
today we have a very good idea of the
size of various
subatomic particles so that is how it's
done this is all about experimental
physics
good question
joy saxena asks my views on the rosewell
roosevelt ufo incident in the usa uh
they found
alien ships and their remains but then
moved them
to some secret location they must have
been in contact with
them that's a very interesting question
so how many of you actually believe that
aliens have actually visited the our
planet just say yes or no in the
comments
do you actually believe that aliens have
visited our planet
because when i was a kid i was
fascinated with this i wanted to read
about aliens all the time
you know alien encounters and all that
so yeah it's very interesting
no no abi says yes cervix says yes anand
says yes
ramana says yes uh aryan says yes
wine gaming says no arjun says no
cherry says yes so i think most of us
harshada says no
i think hersh says possibly
i think the overall consensus seems to
be towards
a belief or or yet towards a belief that
aliens must have visited us
i i am a little skeptical about this
right because we don't have hard
evidence
so here's my view on the rosewell okay
first of all what do we know about this
incident
so this is something that happened in
1947 i think okay
uh in the first half of the year in
1947.
so what happened was that some uh
something crashed from the sky
which looked like it was out of from out
of the earth it was nothing like
something
it was nothing that would be made on the
earth that sort of thing
it was metallic the the crash debris
were metallic and
very strange and it was even announced
in the local newspaper that the local
police department or whoever the
authorities were
they had recovered a crashed flying
saucer
that i think that was the headline in
the newspaper and a couple of days later
it was changed to
say that this was actually a weather
balloon
and there's been allegations of a
cover-up for decades this this has been
going on
and uh people said it is alleged by
various people that uh
it was indeed a ufo and there were even
aliens
in there a couple of aliens that died
and maybe one or two were
were recovered alive and they were taken
away somewhere they were alien autopsies
of autopsies apparently
and so on and then all the debris of
this
flying saucer were carted off somewhere
else and they maybe are in area 51
or something like that so that is what
is believed by a great many people
now the u.s authorities deny this they
say it was a weather balloon
so there was something called project
mogul that was going on at the time
so this was a project in which the
americans would
uh place high sensitive microphones and
other
equipment on weather balloons high up in
the atmosphere
in the with the aim of listening to
certain kinds of
sonic signals acoustic signals signals
that would indicate
a far away nuclear explosion so we know
that the soviets and the americans were
engaged in this nuclear arms race
the soviets were testing nuclear weapons
at the time it was done
these were atmospheric tests which means
that these weapons nuclear weapons were
detonated above the surface of the earth
later on it was mostly underground but
at the time it was atmospheric tests
and these sound waves of these
explosions would travel around the globe
but after they went far enough they
would not really
uh be that detectable
so the aim of project mogul was to place
highly sensitive microphones and other
equipment high up
in the atmosphere on weather balloons
and
listen for such signals and the us
authorities say they
that it was one of these weather
balloons with all the assorted equipment
that crashed in roosevelt new mexico and
and the equipment was highly scientific
and all that various kinds of
complicated
apparatuses all that and that's why it
looked like it's something from out of
the
out of the world so that's what the us
government
clarified in the 1990s i think so there
were some clarifications that were
there were issues in the issued by the
authorities u.s authorities
in the 1990s or i think in the 1990s
and yet there's been a lot of skepticism
about that so people
many people still believe that there's a
cover-up that has happened
so how what do i know i mean unless
you're part of some secret society
ashok's nine secret men or something you
know unless you're part of that
you won't know about this so i don't
know okay whatever information we have
is in the public domain
uh the american authorities say that
it's been debunked comprehensively
ufo logists they say that it's not been
debunked and they are
trying to cover it up so the uh jury is
still
out there i am skeptical by nature
that's what you have to be as a
scientist you have to be skeptical you
have to always look at the
more rational explanation and i would
say that
the more rational explanation would be a
weather balloon or something like that
and yet there is always the possibility
they have i don't think they have been
able to
comprehensively prove that this was just
a weather balloon it's just a claim
it's one claim another against another
came claim so
unless we actually are given the
evidence
we can't really tell so i think the jury
is still out there 90 percent i would
say it's not an
alien thing but maybe 10 it may have
been
so that's where i am about this i am
skeptical but i am still open-minded it
possibly may have been an alien
spacecraft but
so so the uh evidence may have been even
destroyed by now
we don't know where it is so how do we
prove that aliens have visited or are
visiting
well we have to find good evidence today
uh these days you have all this uh
media frenzy about alien visitations
ufos and all that
especially in north america i think only
in north america
so i would like to see evidence from
that not from the us government but from
civilian sources
something that some alien ufo phenomenon
that is captured
on camera not black and white grainy
footage but proper footage and not just
one person but many people
simultaneously then i would really
believe it
so that's what we still seek and so
that's where we are today
as as regards with regards to ufos
aditya asks could there be intelligent
life on proxima centauri b
does intelligent alien life only mean
super advanced aliens i mean they could
also be in their medieval
ages or something like that a good
question so
let's so what is proxima centauri b
so the uh nearest star system
to our own is the proxima centauri
alphas and the
it is that star system it's about four
light years
away from here four four and a half
light years away from our solar system
and they have recently discovered a
planet i mean there's a number of
planets there
exoplanets around this star system i
think it's a triple star system it's
three stars
okay in this system some you usually
have a single star like the sun
sometimes you have a double star system
but in the case of the proxima centauri
system there are three stars
in the system and you have a bunch of
planets around them and one of these
planets is proxima centauri b
so it is in orbit around the main parent
star which is a red dwarf
now this main star is a very small
very cool very dim star it's a red dwarf
it is about 10 percent of the mass of
the sun roughly
and this exoplanet is in the habitable
zone it's about
20 times closer to this to its star than
vr to our sun
right so that's the thing and this
exoplanet is about
is slightly larger in mass than the
earth it's between
1.2 it's between 1.2 and 3
earth masses so now we don't exactly
know what are the conditions on this
planet it is in the habitable zone which
means that if
that running water would be available
there if there is actually indeed any
water on the planet
now there are certain things that we
need to
know further are the is this planet
tidally locked with the star so what is
tidal locking
it's like the earth moon system the uh
time that it takes for the moon to
rotate on its axis is the time that it
takes to revolve around the earth
so one rotation is exactly equal to one
revolution and that's why it is tidally
locked with the earth
and we only see one face of the moon
right so this is something that happens
over time in this in such systems so in
case
this planet proxima centauri b is
tidally locked
with its parent star then one
side of this planet would be permanently
facing that star
and the other side would be permanently
in darkness in that case you would have
a very strange scenario
in which in which half the planet is
very is hot
and half the planet is freezing so that
would not be conducive
to life on the planet the other thing is
that it's very close to the star
and therefore solar flares from its
parent star
may be uh may be a threat to any
possible life on the planet
unless it has a strong magnetic field in
which case these
solar flares stellar flares would not be
that much of a problem
so there are a number of situations
circumstances parameters that we need to
know before we can
tell whether there is life or not on
this planet
uh does intelligent life mean only super
advanced aliens not at all
uh intelligent like i mean i would
consider even a dog or a cat or a
dolphin or a whale
to be reasonably intelligent right i
mean we can communicate with dogs and
cats
they are different kinds of animals i
mean even veils we can communicate
with whales they seem to have
intelligence reasonably good
intelligence
they even seem to have emotions many
animals do
so there are different levels of
intelligence and different levels of
consciousness
so i would not say that only super
intelligent
aliens would would be would constitute
intelligent life
i mean 500 years ago this
world our planet was in a very different
condition right and still it was
our intelligence level was very much the
same
so yes if there are intelligent beings
somewhere then it could be that it could
it's very possible that they could be in
the medieval ages or something like that
and they may not have the kind of
technology
that we have today it is possible so i
hope that answers this question
okay indeed last uh what's
what's your take on the fermi paradox
and the great filter is it possible that
the great filter
is ahead of us that's a very good
question so let's let's first
look at the question of what is the
fermi paradox right
what's the fermi paradox so it's
basically about the
occurrence or not of intelligent life
out there in the universe
so we know that there are about 100
billion
galaxies in the observable universe
based on the data that we have about 100
billion which is
one with 11 zeros after it right and we
know that there are approximately
roughly
100 billion stars per galaxy roughly
you know so that would mean that there
are about 10 to the 22 power of stars in
the universe which means one with 22
zeros after it
these many stars in the universe now
let's say only one percent of these
stars are sun-like stars for the sake of
argument
then you would have 10 raised to 20 such
sun-like stars
and let's say only one percent of these
stars have earth-like planets
then you would have 10 raised to 18
earth-like planets in the observable
universe
and let's say one percent of these
planets would develop
life then you would have 10 so 16
life-bearing planets
in the universe and let's say one
percent of this would develop human-like
intelligence
which would give us about a hundred
trillion
human-like intelligence bearing planets
in the observable universe and if you do
the same calculation for the milky way
you get something between 4000 to
1 lakh human-like intelligent
civilizations
in our own milky way right so then the
question
is if you have these many
possible human-like civilizations in our
own milky way then the question is where
are
all the aliens where are they
why do we see no signs of these aliens
and that
is called the fermi paradox our
calculations tell us that there should
be
an abundance of human level intelligent
life
in our galaxy and in the observable
universe and yet we have seen not
a single sign of that a single sign of
that
that's the fermi paradox so how do we
resolve this paradox right and that is
where we come to these filters
so there is one possibility which which
says that there are no higher
civilizations
in the universe there are no higher
civilizations than
us in existence anywhere because there
is a great
filter so what is this great filter it
is an evolutionary
wall that destroys life once you advance
to a certain stage
maybe it's nuclear war maybe you kill
each other because of some other
form of warfare maybe it's some disease
or maybe life just isn't meant to evolve
past a certain stage so that's called
the great filter
right the possibility too is that we are
a very rare civilization or in
the level of our intelligence is very
rare in the universe
which would essentially indicate that
this great filter is behind us
we have managed to surpass this great
filter
it says that it is extremely rare for
life to make it to our level of
intelligence
right so maybe this great filter that is
spoken about could be at the very
beginning of existence
maybe it's incredibly unusual for life
to begin at all
so maybe we are the first uh life that
exists out there so
that is one of the uh possibilities
right there is another possibility which
says that the great filter has not yet
come up
we have still not come across the gate
filter which means that basically we are
in trouble because the great filter is
ahead of us
it's there in the future and we're going
to run into the great filter
and it's going to annihilate our
existence
i mean we know that we have had many
species of human beings on our planet
homo habilis homo erectus homonia
anderthalis
uh the denisovans australopithecus rdp
takers and so many more
so many species of humans and hominids
came before us
we have some of their genes in us
and yet they have gone extinct as
distinct
species so they run into some filter
right
so that's what we mean by the filter so
maybe there is a filter ahead of us in
the future which means we are screwed
basically
right and then there is another there
are other possibilities that
maybe intelligent civilizations are out
there and maybe there are some good
logical reasons why we have not heard
from them or we have not been able to
detect them
maybe uh maybe super intelligent life
may already have visited earth but maybe
they did
before we evolved as humans and maybe
before we
became intelligent enough so maybe they
came before us
perhaps okay or maybe the galaxy has
been colonized
by a kardashev type 2 civilization but
we just
live in some some desolate rural area of
the galaxy that nobody cares about yeah
so that's another possibility
and maybe there are some extremely
dangerous predator-like civilizations
out there
and most intelligent life
knows that we should not broadcast any
outgoing signals
and advertise where we are and maybe we
are extremely
naive to be advertising our existence
to whatever is out there or whoever is
out there and then there is a
possibility maybe we are receiving some
contact from
intelligent life but our governments are
hiding it
right so there are a number of such uh
possibilities maybe there are
civilizations so advanced
that we are too primitive to perceive
them you know
so these are the possibilities and so
that is what the great filters are this
is the fermi paradox
and that is this entirety what i just
outlined is the uh kind of debate
that is ongoing about this matter
akash asks is mathematics invented or
discovered
what are the chances for example that
the area of the circle of a circle is
pi squared for every advanced
civilization in the universe if they
exist
so to answer this question we have to
first ask ourselves
what is mathematics what is it
so mathematics is
something that expresses the
patterns and the regularities in the
universe
it is a language that expresses these
patterns and regularities in the
universe
right so the universe has patterns and
regularities and
mathematics is a language that perhaps
we have invented
to express in the
simplest possible form and the most
concise possible form
these patterns and regularities so we
are discovering
these patterns and regularities but we
are expressing them
in a language that maybe we have
invented right
so we do discover things in mathematics
and we also invent techniques
to discover things in mathematics right
so if there are intelligent aliens out
there maybe they use different notation
for doing their mathematics so maybe
it's a language it's a different
language that they've invented and it's
a different language that we have
invented
right but these languages whatever they
are
they do express the same things about
three words the same patterns and
regularities so mathematics is invented
it is also discovered because we are
discovering
facts about the universe for example
mathematicians are always several steps
ahead of physicists
they talk about infinite dimensional
spaces they talk about various things
that physicists have no use for
and then 100 years out down the line we
suddenly find a use
for one of these things that
mathematicians have been doing
supposedly random abstract things that
mathematicians have been playing with
you know
for example you have group theory galwa
theory which was discovered in the 19th
century
or discovered invented whatever you call
it by a french teenager
right and for a hundred years it has it
had no application of any kind it was it
was something abstruse
and abstract and suddenly today with the
in the 20th century it found a great use
in particle physics you know
in symmetry in the in the symmetric
symmetric groups in particle physics
so so that's an example of how ahead of
the times mathematicians are
so they discover things about the
universe regularities and symmetries of
the universe
and they express them in the language of
mathematics and like i said
they also invent tools and
techniques to solve problems which allow
them which enable them to make
discoveries about the universe
for example you have various
differential equations and tools
and techniques of solving differential
equations in matrices and numerical
analysis and whatnot
so these are tools that are invented to
make discoveries so i would say that
mathematics is both
invented and discovered it does tell us
something very profound about the
universe
it does help us understand the universe
better there's only one mathematics
there are no
parallel branches of mathematics that
differ from each other 2 plus 2 is
always 4
and the area of the circle is always pi
r
squared right so unless
you're on a curved surface in which case
it's something else so in
so in in curved geometry the area of a
circle is different etcetera or a
triangle etcetera you know so that's how
it is
so for example pythagoras theorem we
know what it is on on a flat surface
it's different on a curved surface but
that
holds true for the entire observable
universe as far as we know
so to make it short i think mathematics
is something that
is invented as well as discovered tools
and techniques of mathematics are
are invented but the deep underlying
patterns and regularities of the
universe
that mathematics expresses are actually
discovered
so that's what mathematics is it is the
it is
the most logical language that we have
and it's the language of
physics so there's no physics without
mathematics
[Music]
asks can we create life using science or
is there a soul atma that's a good
question so
people have been trying to do various
chemical experiments
to try and replicate the environment
that was present in the very early earth
when the earth was very young
about four billion or so years ago the
earth is about four four and a half
billion years old if i'm not in very
mistaken you know roughly
that much and the very early earth was
very different from
what it is today it was it was hell we
would find it hell you know that's how
it was it was a very hot
dense swirling environment
there was a lot of bombardment happening
from the from space because of
various impacts from space debris from
the early solar system
the atmospheric composition was very
different the planet was very hot
the gases were different and all that
and that is the environment in which
life first emerged
on our planet so scientists chemists
biochemists etc
they try to replicate that environment
environment in a test tube
and they try to create various and they
try to see if life can emerge from there
so what they find is that various
uh complex organic
compounds carbon compounds do emerge
from that even amino acids
etc they do emerge from these
experiments when you take these
this mixture of gases and liquids and
you put them in a test tube and you
heat them to a certain certain
temperature or you pass electricity
through them and all that and keep doing
that for hours or days
then you find that complex chemistry
does arise out of it and yet we have
never been
actually able to to create life you know
unicellular life or anything like that
out of it thus far so thus far it seems
that we are
unable to create life out of chemicals
and chemistry and
using science thus far it's not been
possible
maybe it may be possible in the future
we don't know the exact
origin of life on our planet did it
actually
emerge spontaneously in the
primeval atmos atmosphere and
environment of our planet
or is it something that was seeded from
outside from a cometary impact
is it some this depends the panspermia
theory says that
dna and the seeds of life may have come
from
from interstellar space because we find
that certain
asteroids and meteors and even comets
contain
complex carbon compounds organic
compounds even amino acids
etc that are we know they are the
building blocks of
of organic life so the jury is still out
there we don't know
where life came from thus far we have
been unable
to create synthetic life forms
using chemistry biochemistry etc so
as of today it's not possible in the
future we don't know it
may perhaps be possible and now what
about the soul well the soul
uh there is a dividing line between
science and philosophy
right science is a subset
of philosophy but philosophy so science
is a part of philosophy but philosophy
is not a part of science and
spirituality again is not part of
science
science deals with observable phenomena
and physical objects only that is the
limitation
of science it has very hard boundaries
only physical objects
only observable phenomena now the soul
is not a physical object
i think everybody would agree and it's
not an observable phenomenon
right we cannot see the soul we can't
measure it we can't detect it we don't
know its properties
it doesn't have physical properties it
is believed to be something that
transcends the physical world
right and therefore it is not something
that science can describe
or experiment or even talk about it is
something that belongs in the realm of
philosophy and spirituality
i am not in any way denigrating
the um the concept of the soul or i am
in no way trying to
mock anybody who believes in the soul
i think most people on this planet
believe that
there are souls in human beings another
other be other also
other beings as well i'm sure even lots
of scientists believe it whether they
express that belief or not but the
concept of the soul
is not something that's part of science
and therefore i cannot answer the
question as a scientist
whether whether there's a solo or not as
far as we know we have never seen any
experimental evidence or observational
evidence
of the existence of the soul and yet
one cannot rule it out even from the
perspective of science
something that has not been observed the
doesn't mean it doesn't exist the
absence of evidence is not the evidence
of absence
right so the soul is something that is
beyond science
maybe in the future someday science may
advance that much that
we may actually be able to uh perhaps
detect
the soul if it does exist or not but as
of today i can't say i have no evidence
that the soul exists or doesn't exist
right so that's where we are from the
perspective of science
today
okay according to johann rockstrom
we have only three years to reverse the
growth in greenhouse gas emissions
if we are going to reach the goals set
in the paris agreement
this was said in 2018. my question is
what if we fail to meet the goals of the
paris agreement
will it be too late for humanity to
survive on earth
and do we ultimately have to find
another planet for our species
okay so i'm not very sure about what
were the exact goals given in the paris
climate agreement
unfortunately nobody in
the leadership positions of of various
nations
especially the geopolitically powerful
nobody takes climate change seriously
climate change is uh well it's not taken
seriously geopolitical goals are more
important than climate change
and it's very clear that whatever goals
were set in the paris climate agreement
are not going to be met greenhouse gas
emission emissions continue to uh
happen and global warming is is a fact
so we are going to
have continuing global warming and
in a century or two the planet will be
several degrees
warmer than what it is today that is
going to happen
there is nothing that is being done to
stop it and it may even not be possible
to stop it because the process of
climate change
through greenhouse gas gas emissions was
set in motion
at least two or three centuries ago with
the industrial revolution
in england and in the western world so
that's where all the emissions came from
it happened for centuries
today they are trying to shift the blame
to the
to the developing countries especially
china and india
but the point is that we are already
beyond
perhaps the point at which we can stop
or
or even stop or reverse the uh
climate change in global warming will
will this make it impossible for
humanity
to survive on earth no not at all
humanity will will continue to survive
humanity
has always adapted and evolved there
have been terrible ice ages in the past
there have been
times of global warming as well in the
past climate change
is has always been there the climate has
always
been changing right now it's happening
because of man-made
processes but in the past it happened
because of other things as well
our ancestors 65 million years ago
survived the worst weekend in living i
mean
in the past hundred years of a hundred
million years of of the earth's history
the churchill impact event which wiped
out the non-avian dinosaurs
there was a terrible climate change
effect event that happened because of
this impact event
there was a nuclear or climate winter
that lasted about 10 years or so
there was no sunlight for that period of
time almost all light
life was wiped out on the planet but our
ancestors those little
little shrew-like mammals they survived
it
so the point is that human beings are
resilient we will survive
but it won't be a good time for us life
as we know it
may not continue to exist our
lifestyles may have to change
drastically maybe there could be uh
maybe there could be population die-offs
in certain parts of the world
in less privileged part of the parts of
the world
so these things may happen there's
nothing we can do to stop it
uh even if every nation were to try and
stop this thing which is not going to
happen
even then we may be at best be able to
slow climate change down
or slow the global warming down
so i think it's currently an
irreversible process we are
on track to see two or three degrees of
warming in the next
50 to 100 years maybe more maybe more
warming i'm not sure
i've not studied the literature but it's
going to happen
the bigger problem is the proliferation
of plastic
in our oceans and in our water sources
basically what we are finding now is
that even bottled water that is purified
etc
contains microplastic particles
and that is going to pose a long-term
health hazard
for us and for our descendants we're
basically poisoning everything with
plastic
the western countries started adopting
plastic about 100 years ago
and they have this culture that is like
a disposable culture everything is to be
used once and then thrown away
and all of it was dumped into the oceans
and today we are paying the price of
that
today you have this enormous mountains
of garbage and plastic floating around
the oceans
so all these things are going to be a
significant factor
in the future of humanity and we still
don't know how it's going to affect us
so as of today this is something that
cannot be changed the paris climate
agreement whatever goals are there are
not going to be met
i think humanity will survive but the
future is going to be very challenging
do we have to will we have to find a
different another planet
well the only planet we have out there
is mars and it's
currently not inhabitable for human
beings
unless you are one of the very small
billionaire class in which case you may
be able to move there
in the next 30 40 50 years but the
common population of earth the
average human being they are doomed if
something wrong
something were to go wrong wrong on the
planet on our planet here
so that is the situation we are in as of
today
aditya asks are we capable of avoiding a
human extinction
extinction by an asteroid as of today
from whatever calculations computations
simulations we have done
we are not in a position to avoid human
extinction
if a sizable asteroid were to be
heading our way so there are a couple of
uh possibilities people have thought of
of destroying an asteroid it always
involves
involves a nuclear weapon take a hundred
megaton or so nuclear weapon
uh throw it shoot it
uh launch it at the incoming asteroid
and detonate the nuclear
weapon near the surface of the asteroid
so they have done simulations of such a
nuclear blast on the surface of an
asteroid and you know what they found
they found that the nuclear blast if it
is powerful enough
will fragment the asteroid the asteroid
will be blasted into small pieces
and it will be blown apart in different
directions
and then gravity will take over
and this and the millions of different
pieces of the asteroid
will reassemble together and it will
become one single asteroid again
so that's what happens when you fragment
an asteroid with a nuclear weapon it
makes no difference whatsoever
its center of mass remains more or less
the same and all the fragments
over time reassemble and within a week
or so you will have the asteroid
reforming and coming towards you as if
nothing
had changed so as of today we can't use
nuclear weapons to
destroy an asteroid even if we destroyed
it it will reassemble like by magic you
know
the other possibility is that of using a
gravity tractor so you send a satellite
or spacecraft
near the asteroid and you use the small
gravity of the spacecraft
to slowly slowly slowly tug the asteroid
away
into a different trajectory
and you do this over a period of a few
months and you do this so that the
trajectory will be just enough so that
it will
instead of hitting the earth miss the
earth so that
is one technology that we have the means
to actually test
it's not been tested yet i think it is
something we should
think about very seriously it is
something we should try out
so that in case we detect an asteroid
like that we can actually
use this technology but as of today as
of as of
the end of july 2021 there is
no way to currently avoid a human
extinction event by an asteroid
narayan asks what are your thoughts on
big
data so big data is these large
enormous social media and other
companies
in the us mostly that aggregate our data
and information you have facebook you
have google
you have instagram which belongs to
facebook i think you have twitter
uh youtube etc so you have all these
different
social media and big data platforms
that have access to our personal
information
they they are able to track our our
doings whatever we do our movements and
whatnot
and basically we are feeding them with
our data
so they know where we are they know our
gps information
they know what kind of browsing history
we have
they know what our likes and dislikes
are they know what we click like on
what we click click thumbs up on they
know what we click thumbs down on
they know where we put our hearts and
whatever else they know what we comment
on they know our browsing habits they
know our shopping habits
they know more about us than we know
ourselves because
all of these disparate points data
points
they they can be aggregated together to
create a very detailed psychological
profile
of every individual and using these
individual psychological profiles
you can create psychological profiles of
entire demographics
males females age great age ranges
geographical regions countries etc
right so if if any organization or any
any power had all of this data
then they would actually be able to see
in real time the mood of a country
or a region in a country they would be
able to
to influence the mood of a country or a
region
just by trending certain things certain
hashtags
certain news stories etc and all of this
data it is extremely valuable because it
can be
mined this data can be mined and
exploited
to make you buy to induce you to buy
certain things or cultivate certain
habits and whatnot
it's enormously powerful data like they
say the
like the cliche goes is the new oil and
all of this data
currently is owned by the united states
all of these companies are u.s companies
and that's what is happening right now
it is a very scary prospect we all
benefit from it it makes our life so
much easier
our cell phone our computer our tablet
knows what
it's like they can read our mind they
know exactly what we want at what time
right and they get they show us
information and things
that make us happy etc but they do this
because they're able to hack into our
into our psyche they're able to read our
psyche and they know us better
than we do there is something called
predictive analysis analytics
so they're able to predict our behavior
in the future
right so that's what big data is
sociology
is passe sociology is obsolete these
teachers in
sociology departments their sociological
theories are
are finished they're of no use anymore
it is
big data that has perfected applied
psychology and applied sociology and
applied psychoanalysis
this big data all of this information
all these data points these
trillions of pieces of data points
that's what
constitutes real psychology real social
analysis and whatnot
right so they are the real sociologists
and psychoanalysts
and that's what they are doing and they
can actually
make the world think differently they
can influence the world
very subtly but the overall effect is
very powerful
so that is what big data is
it is extraordinarily powerful it
permeates everything it doesn't
recognize national boundaries
it doesn't recognize national
sovereignty governments are helpless in
front of it
unless unless you're china because china
has the great fire wall of china and
they don't allow
their data to be shared with the west
and to some extent even russia does that
so the countries that have some
geopolitical standing geopolitical
ambition
countries with good leadership they are
able to
ward off this threat from the united
states and from the west but other
countries
that have well
other countries they don't do it so
india is basically
a thoroughly permeated with the big data
companies
and they know more about us than we know
ourselves so essentially this could very
quickly very soon
and very possibly lead to something
called digital colonization
we will be colonized by
the west without them ever sending a
single soldier
into our physical into our geographical
uh
sovereign region of sovereignty because
software and the internet and big data
doesn't recognize
it doesn't need it transcends
geographical boundaries and political
boundaries
so we are on the verge of digital
colonization it will make
it will basically uh make the rich
richer the powerful more powerful and
the less privileged even less privileged
in those countries that are
geopolitically weak it will make them
weaker it may
render them irrelevant so that is what
big data is it's it is
something that is very useful for the
individual
it makes life very convenient for the
individual and yet on a
geopolitical scale it is a very
significant threat
to the sovereignty and independence and
long-term existence of various countries
okay elon musk's mark zuckerberg jack
dorsey etc support
ubi universal basic income will ubi
be the only source of income when
artificial intelligence
gains consciousness and and
be able to do any kind of human work
creative or routine better than humans
themselves
so you're asking a question about
universal basic income it's something
that many of these uh
billionaires have supported that's what
that's
the kind of thing they are espousing
universal basic income
so you know in the past uh in the 1950s
60s etc
you had these science fiction writers
who had this very utopian view
that advances in science will make
work unnecessary so all the technology
all the science all the robots will do
all the work
and humans will live a life of leisure
they will not have to work
anymore and yet the situation that we
are in today is that we have the means
and the technology to eliminate
a lot of the work that people have to do
and yet the system the capitalist system
is such that
if you don't work then you don't get to
eat
right you have no wages and basically
you are either homeless
or or starving or you are dependent on
handouts
from the state so the system is such
that it
ensure that people
have to work and if you lose your job if
if technological advances
make your job redundant then basically
it's a big problem for you
so the system hasn't evolved with times
the system is supposed to uh
serve the individual but it actually
serves
the state and and the various
individuals
i am not in any way espousing socialism
or marxism i abhor those principles
but capitalism is equally dangerous and
it is equally bad
right so so the one solution that these
people suggest is that everybody is
given
a universal basic income which will
ensure that they can live a life of
of reasonable dignity and reasonable
means they are able to survive etc
and so on so it will basically create
two classes of people
the people who subsist on ubi universal
basic income
and the people who are productive in the
new system and the people who get rich
so it's going to exacerbate the class
divide
the the income divide et cetera that
already exists in the west
the united states has a very high genie
coefficient it's one of the most
unequal countries in the world there is
an enormous disparity between the rich
and the poor they talk about india
well the u.s is far worse that's
something the
western media and even the indian media
want to speak about
so this universal basic income concept
is going to just
well it's not a bad concept it will
ensure that nobody starves
nobody goes homeless and yet it's going
to create this it's going to widen
the divide between the haves and the
have-nots
right so i don't think it's the best
solution we need a better system we need
to
uh evolve a better system a system that
doesn't
exploit people like the way
that capitalism does we need a better
system i don't think ubi is a good
long-term solution we need
we need to change the system ubi ensures
that the
capital system that keeps creating
trillionaires
it it will exist it will keep existing
and they are trying to basically say
that we're going to give you some
handouts
so that you don't feel too aggrieved i
don't think that's the right solution we
need a better
system we need a better solution than
this
okay akash asks about the philadelphia
experiment
a person named carl allen said that the
u.s navy conducted
an experiment in 1943 in which a
destroyer called uss eldridge
vanished from philadelphia naval
shipyard and was seen about 500
kilometers away
in norfolk virginia in an instant and
again
reappear in the shipyard
so this looks like a hoax to me but it's
a popular myth or urban legend
it was deemed possible because the us
military had solved the unified field
theory
with the help of aliens my question is
what is this unified field theory
and what are the chances that this is a
true this was a true incident
so in my understanding of physics
and science there is no technology that
exists today
that can uh make any object disappear
from one place
and appear instantaneously somewhere
else and then reappear back
some in the original location there is
no such
technology in existence as far as i know
so from that understanding i would say
this is a hoax or an urban legend now
there is some talk about the
so-called unified field theory so albert
einstein was working on unifying
uh on unifying quantum mechanics
and general relativity so that's what we
are still trying to do
as physicists we are trying to find a
unified
what's called the grand unified theory
the unified theory field theory is
something similar to that so that's what
albert einstein was working on
he was never able to create
a unified field theory he was never able
to discover this unified
theory he was never able to unify these
two very disparate
pieces of branches of physics together
so it's never been done and even if he
was able to unify
to to create a unified field theory what
are the applications of that
how do we know that the application is
that we can make objects
operate elsewhere instantaneously
right so there's a it basically um
goes against every known law and
principle of
physics there was even some talk about
sailors having
becoming sailors merging with the
infrastructure of the ship their arms
and legs and limbs becoming entangled
with the hull and all that
so uh there is no technology that we
know of
that is capable of doing this and the
unified field theory
is still something we are searching for
it's something we are still seeking
nobody has been able to unify quantum
mechanics and general relativity right
and the best
field theory that we have as of today is
quantum field theory
now there is no actual practical
application
of this sort in quantum field theory
and therefore my conclusion from what i
know
is that this has to be either a hoax or
what do you call it an
urban legend right there is no
hard evidence that has been provided
that this actually happened and there is
no way it can actually happen this
basically is something that would happen
in not in science fiction but in fantasy
so from my perspective it is 99.999
a hoax or an urban legend
harsh asks what is the barrier that
humans are facing in exploring the earth
as a whole as there are great unknowns
in both the ocean
and on land although we have we think
that we may have mapped
most of the land mass and how will
humankind hope to explore other planets
when the project of mapping
and exploring their own planet is
incomplete
so first of all even if the project of
mapping your own planet is incomplete
it's definitely possible
for us to land on the moon and soon on
mars as well
so it's something we can certainly do
but you are absolutely right hurst that
we
we don't know much about our own planet
we don't know
i think more than 90 percent of the
oceans are unmapped
we know the we have a topographic
map of the bottom of the oceans right we
are able to
map the bottoms the the the bottom of
the ocean
with various technologies but we don't
really know what's going on in there
we know how deep it is what are the
shapes and contours of the underwater
undersea mountains and valleys and
canyons and all that
but we don't know what species of life
live
live down there most of it is in
darkness
i think below 100 or about 300 meters
the ocean is permanently in darkness
there's no sunlight that reaches there
so there's a lot i think more than 90 of
the ocean is completely unknown to us we
don't know what species live there we
don't know what's going on in there
uh there's this aircraft that
disappeared somewhere and it's never
been found
the uh malaysian airlines m
370 was it that one a few years ago
there was an indian air force plane that
disappeared somewhere in the bay of
bengal we never found it
so the ocean is a big mystery it's very
hard to find things in there
so you are right we don't know much of
the surface of our planet we don't know
much of the
the the oceans we don't know much of the
oceans
the surface of the planet we know most
of it
but we don't know what happens inside
our planet i mean even if we
were to dig a hole 10 kilometers deep we
would find something new and completely
unexpected down there
i'm sure recently we have found exist
the evidence
we have found evidence of microbes that
have been
embedded in rock that is millions of
years old
and those microbes are not dead so we
are finding
staggering new discoveries such as these
right and we don't exactly know
the the internal composition of the
of our planet we have a good idea that
we have
there is a molten uh layer of magma
then you have other layers you have
a core that is the outer core which is
of liquid metal the inner core which is
solid metal
which is very strange unusual properties
etc
and there is an electric field there is
a magnetic field that is generated
because of this uh internal
structure this liquid core etc
and yet it's all based on inferences
we haven't really gone and explored
these parts of our planet so you are
absolutely right
we know very little about our planet
it's like there is a ball on which you
have a bunch of ants
and they think they know everything
about it actually they don't know
anything about the planet
so that is the kind of situation that
human beings are in we don't even
understand our
own planet to any great degree
so that's where we are there are great
unknowns like you say
but it doesn't it's not going to prevent
us from going to other planets
and exploring those as well so that's
going to happen for sure
indu asks technology and artificial
intelligence are
replacing unskilled laborers in almost
all the industries will the amount of
employment that the tech industry
creates
equalize or offset the amount that it
takes so what you're saying is that
technology artificial intelligence and
all that
are making lots of jobs
redundant right
and uh basically these are the unskilled
uh jobs jobs that unskilled people would
do
those are the those are the first ones
to become redundant
eventually jobs that
require greater skills and proficiency
will also
start becoming redundant that is the
direction in which we are going
there is nothing we can do to stop this
progress of technology
all we can do is evolve and
adapt adapt and evolve so for example
when the industrial revolution happened
in the west in england etc lots of jobs
were made
redundant so people had to reskill
themselves they had to learn new skills
and adapt to the new uh environment and
situation
so similarly as of today lots of
unskilled jobs
will disappear soon within this decade
is going to happen
we can't stop it so the only alternative
the only thing we can do as people is to
adapt and evolve
the people who don't have skills need to
find ways to
skill themselves learn new skills and
learn skills that are that are
relevant and valuable in this new
high-tech environment
and age that we are living in so that's
what needs to happen
we need we need as
governments our governments need to
ensure
that they provide the means
for these unskilled people to acquire
new skills
and not just skills like carpentry or
gardening or something but i mean
high-tech skills
that's what takes a country forward
farming is not a skill that takes the
country forward
so i would like to see governments in
various countries including our own
country india
to provide sufficient opportunities
for people who lack the skills to
acquire those skills
and that's how we are able going to be
able to mitigate this problem
but to answer your question in brief
this new technological
environment this new technological
paradigm that we are in it's not going
to create new jobs it's going to take
away jobs
so it's going to be a problem for
countries that don't don't adapt
and evolve so that is what needs to
happen that is the solution
kosto asks are you satisfied with the
copenhagen interpretation of quantum
mechanics as
it's the most successful
notion of the theory till today or do
you consider the manny world's
interpretation to be a bright
prospect so the copenhagen
interpretation
is uh is the great victory of niels bohr
over
albert einstein there was this great set
of debates these two
uh towering scientific towering
physicists had
in the in the 1920s and 30s
i don't remember the exact time frame
but they had these debates about the
meaning of quantum mechanics
so when the this new science emerged
quantum mechanics it was all bits and
pieces they were trying to put things
together they were trying to understand
what it is telling us and slowly first
you had the
the notion of the quantum that that
energy is quantized that you have a
quantum
of light called the photon then you had
the uh then you found if it was found
that energy levels in atoms are
quantized the atom was discovered
electron
proton neutron etc then there was a bohr
model of the atom
and so on and so forth but the question
was what does quantum mechanics tell us
there are these these uh great paradoxes
you had wave particle duality particle
of
a partic a particle can be a particle it
can be a wave at the same time
right a photon is a particle as well as
a wave and so the same for any other
particle right
so you had this thing then you had the
problem of the collapse of the wave
function
a particle doesn't doesn't have any
properties when it is not being observed
it is just a set of probabilities so
these properties are meaningless unless
you observe it
it doesn't even exist in one place at
the same time when it is not being
observed
and when you make an observation when
you make a measurement the wave function
of the particle collapses into one
single state
before that it was a superposition of
states so the copenhagen interpretation
of quantum mechanics says that
the properties of a particle have no
meaning
before a measurement is made it's just a
set of mathematical probabilities
so a particle the properties of a
particle are meaningless
until and unless you make a measurement
or an observation
and albert einstein was against that he
said that properties should exist and he
proposed
a number of other alternatives
so according to the copenhagen
interpretation particles
uh the the the measurement or
observation of a particle causes the
collapse of the wave function
and before that the particle doesn't
really exist it's just a set of
probabilities
and it is best expressed in this famous
line
shut up and calculate don't ask
philosophical questions of what the
particle was doing
before you observe it just calculate use
the laws
of quantum mechanics to calculate uh
whatever you're calculating and that's
how you make progress and that's how all
the quantum
mechanics based technologies have
evolved that made
the 21st century possible so it's been a
very successful
interpretation most
physicists believed in this
interpretation until recently
now you have more and more physicists
who are
leaning towards the many worlds
interpretation which which is due to
hugh
everett uh who was a
so hugh everett is the physicist who put
forward this
competing interpretation of quantum
mechanics which says that every time a
measurement
or observation is made the wave function
seems to collapse but it's actually
branching off into two different parts
into in two parallel universes into into
parallel worlds
so what you see the collapsed wave
function is what you see in this
this specific universe but in other
branches
of the timeline of the particle the
other possibilities
are still present so every time you make
an observation the world splits off into
two universes
every time you think about something
every time you make a decision or a
choice every time you flip a coin
the world splits into two branches so
that is
in very brief and very roughly the many
worlds interpretation of quantum
mechanics
it is physically consistent there is
nothing
wrong with it if you examine it properly
and deeply
so what is my stand i think the many
worlds interpretation is very
is very interesting i think the quantum
the copenhagen
interpretation is limited
i am sure that there is more to quantum
mechanics than just
a set of probabilities of a particle
when it when it is not being observed
there has to be something more that's my
gut feeling and that's a good feeling of
many
physicists so i am
well i would think that the many worlds
interpretation is very interesting and
it should be something that should be
investigated further
so uh i am not
firmly in favor of one or the other but
i think the many worlds interpretation
is very interesting
as are some other interpretations of
quantum mechanics the copenhagen
interpretation interpretation has been
very successful in taking
science forward it's been successful
in putting away the philosophical
questions and just calculating
and making further discoveries so from
that perspective it's been brilliant but
there are many unanswered questions and
those have to be addressed
and the many world interpretation is is
is one step in that direction
i think a lot of ground needs to be
covered but that's where we are today
priyam asks the big bank should have
created equal amounts of matter
and antimatter but we don't find it to
be so
a hypothesis says that all this vanished
antimatter is what
helped primordial black holes to grow
into ultra massive black holes quasars
such as ton 618 which is 66 billion
solar masses
etc um
so it may be even bigger now so can you
please explain this so what you are
asking is about
why do we only observe regular matter
in the universe why don't we observe
antimatter the universe
should have created the big bang
should have created equal amounts of
matter and antimatter we expect the
universe to be neutral
right charge neutral matter neutral all
that
and therefore where is the antimatter
so one of the proposed solutions to this
problem is that maybe
maybe antimatter exists in the
non-observable universe maybe there are
regions of the universe in which
matter regular matter predominates and
maybe there are
regions of the universe where antimatter
predominates
so and maybe we are not able to see
those maybe because maybe the the actual
universe is much larger than the
observable universe and maybe the
antimatter is somewhere else beyond our
cosmic
horizon that is one possibility the
other possibility
the other theory or hypothesis is that
the big bang gave rise to two universes
a regular universe and an anti-universe
so the regular universe contains regular
matter the
matter that we are made of and the
entire universe
contains anti-matter
and it's the kind of universe where time
flows backward or whatever right
so that's another hypothesis so that
could possibly
explain this problem so this
uh problem that you speak about is
called the baryon asymmetry problem
or the matter antimatter asymmetry
problem as of today we don't have an
explanation
for why matter predominates or
antimatter
there are a number of theories like i
said but none of them has been proven
thus far so it is an
open unsolved problem
in physics as of today
akash asks why is there such a huge
temperature difference between the sun's
north
and south poles good question so
from what i recall that there is a
several percentage
maybe six seven maybe even ten percent i
don't think ten percent but a few
percentage points of of
temperature difference between the north
pole and the south pole i think the
south pole of the sun is currently
hotter than the north pole
a few percent hotter and what is the
reason
what what causes this is the question so
if you look at the earth for example
even the earth has a temperature
differential
i think the north pole is warmer than
the south pole
in the case of the earth we know that
the it's because of the
difference in the distribution of land
mass in the northern hemisphere in the
south
in the southern hemisphere there is much
more land mass on the northern
hemisphere
and there's much more oceans in the
southern hemisphere
and that is one of the reasons why the
southern hemisphere is cooler and the
south pole is colder
than the north pole on the earth now we
know that these sun's
um polar regions are
where the magnetic field of the sun
comes out and that's where the solar
wind emerges to some extent so maybe
it's a magnetic phenomenon that causes
the difference difference in temperature
and it's been observed that when the
solar magnetic field
flips every 11 or 14 years i think it's
every 11 years
so even when the magnetic field flips
the temperature differential of the
sun's poles
also flips so it is clearly something
that's related to the magnetic field of
the sun
it is driven by magnetism but the exact
mechanism
is thus far unknown so as of today we
don't have a clear answer of why
we have a temperature difference in the
poles of the sun what causes this
we know it is related to magnetism it is
some magnetic
mechanism that is causing this but what
exactly it is
we don't know because we can't we are
unable to look inside the sun
we have certain spacecraft near the sun
which are observing it
but we can't really uh gorge what's
happening
within the sun we have an idea of of the
interior
of the sun there is a convection zone
and there's the core of the sun
and all that we know that it takes maybe
a million years for a photon to actually
emerge out of the sun
after it's produced but there is a lot
about the interior structure of the sun
that is not known to us what are the
processes what are the mechanisms
we still don't know uh very well
so even this this question as of today
is still
an open problem it's a mystery
me mandar asks string theory is failing
what do you think will replace it
so string theory is a theory that can be
considered to have
failed i'm not saying it is entirely
completely wrong
it is well motivated the motivation is
good it is to find a theory that unifies
quantum field theory and gravitation
but the problem is that string theory is
extraordinarily complicated the
mathematics is very
and that is not the only problem it
doesn't make any testable predictions
and it is not falsifiable a good
scientific theory or
any scientific theory has to be
falsifiable
and it has to make testable predictions
string theory
does neither of these things and that's
why many scientists many physicists
today are of the opinion that it is time
to move
beyond string theory so what will
replace it as
of today we don't have good alternatives
to replace it
the objective is to find a way
to reconcile quantum field theory
with a general relativity
to make these quantum fields work
in curved space time so we have not
been able to find a way of doing this
string theory was a step in the
direction another theory
which is a step in the stage in the same
direction is
loop quantum gravity i have a video on
loop quantum gravity on this channel
you can check it out so loop quantum
gravity is
a theory that seeks to solve this
problem as of today it's not able to do
that
but it is a good development so to
answer your question in brief as of
today we don't know what will replace
string theory string theory itself is
not a very valuable theory it's not
really
given us any solutions or any answers to
the big problems
right so what we seek is a theory that's
able to reconcile quantum field theory
with general relativity it will be a
step in the direction
of grand unified theory so
so what should replace it eventually is
a theory that
reconciles quantum field theory with
general relativity as of today we are
nowhere near that but i think loop
quantum gravity is interesting it could
be a step in the right direction
okay so why are scientists trying to
merge gravity and quantum physics even
though gravity is just
the curvature of space-time so here's
the motivation of
trying to find a theory that unifies or
reconciles
quantum field theory with general
relativity which basically like you said
is in a way the curvature of space-time
it's how
mass affects space-time how mass curves
space-time
and it's also about how curved space
time tells mass how to move
so that is general relativity quantum
field theory is about the 17
known fields of the various particles of
the standard model
so why are we trying to merge this
because we are trying to do this because
there are lots of
there are a number of very prominent
and very massive unsolved problems
in physics we have two glaring issues
there is dark matter and there is dark
energy dark matter is something that
comprises about
20 25 percent how much is it
24 of of the matter of the universe i
may have a percentage wrong
don't dead don't uh hold me to that
20 24 is dark matter approximately
of the entire matter energy composition
of the universe
and about 70 or 71 percent of the matter
energy composition
of the universe is dark energy and we
don't have a
clue as to what dark matter is or what
dark energy is
so only four percent roughly of the
universe
is what we see 96 percent
is invisible it's dark we don't have a
clue as to what it
is and it is something that that seems
to interact
with ordinary matter gravitationally
so it ha it is something linked to
gravitation it seems to
only interact through gravitation and
not through the other
other three forces there are four known
forces the strong nuclear force
the weak nuclear force electromagnetism
and gravity
so this dark matter seems to interact
only gravitationally it doesn't seem to
feel the other three forces
and dark energy is even more mysterious
it is it seems to be a repulsive form of
gravity it seems to be
anti-gravity of some kind
and it is there everywhere it permeates
all of space-time it permeates all of
our universe
and we don't have the faintest idea of
what it is and that is why
because we only understand four percent
of the universe and that too very poorly
that is the reason why we are trying to
find better
theories of physics and the
thinking is and the thinking is right
that if we are able to
find a theory that reconciles quantum
field theory
and general relativity then we will get
better insights
into the into the uh
nature into the true nature of our
universe there are so many problems we
don't understand what black holes are
according to general relativity there is
a if there's a singularity
inside black holes a point of infinite
density and infinite curvature which is
unphysical so clearly general relativity
breaks down in um
in this in this region of space inside
black holes
so these are the problems in physics
today and that's why we are trying to
reconcile
general relativity with quantum field
theory which will basically give us a
better
idea of what our universe is like
so that is the motivation for for doing
this and that's it's it's very important
that we do this
to understand our universe better
ayush asks what is negative mass so
negative mass is something that has
never been observed
but yeah you can play around with the
mathematics in
in equations of physics and yeah you can
you can basically try and see what are
the um
what are the properties of negative mass
so i think i have
spoken about wormholes in a previous
episode i think i have a small clip
about that
so wormholes are something that tend to
pinch off they want to close
shut and to keep a wormhole open one of
the solutions is to use some kind of
exotic matter
to keep that tunnel open and one of the
proposed solutions is to use
negative mass so negative mass
is something that would have a repulsive
action
we know that gravity is attractive if i
have a pen
and i leave it like that it's going to
fall down it's going to go towards the
center of the earth
so that's a repulsive that's an
attractive force the center of mass of
the earth
attracts this mass towards it that's
an attractive force in the case of a
negative mass it would actually
repel a positive mass such as this
so that would be a repulsive form of
gravity
so if negative mass does exist
somewhere it would repel
uh regular masses normal masses so
that's what negative masses
and how do we know it would be repulsive
we just have to put a negative sign
in the uh in the equation for the
gravitational potential and we see that
it causes a repulsive effect
so that's what negative mass is we have
never observed any sign
or evidence that it actually exists
somewhere in the universe
but from the point of perspective of
mathematics and physics it's not
something that's impossible one could
have it it does fit into the equations
of physics
and it does produce the effect of
repulsive gravity
dominic asks what is the future for
students in india who look forward to
becoming astronauts as of today only
test pilots in the indian air force are
eligible to be astronauts
because you need a certain certain set
of
attributes mental attributes
psychological attributes and physical
attributes
to be able to become an astronaut and
military test pilots
have all those attributes right so as of
today it's military test pilots who are
being
uh trained for the indian human space
flight
program which may take off in the next
couple of years maybe the first
flight of indian people
indian astronauts will take place in the
next two or three years at most i think
from what i hear so as of today you have
to be a military
an air force test pilot in the future if
india
does decide to augment
its human space flight program if it
becomes more ambitious
in space exploration then maybe you
would find
maybe scientists or engineers
or biologists or chemists or physicists
traveling into space as astronauts
that could happen and in the future
maybe space tourism may take off in in
which case if you are very rich
you may be able to buy a ticket into
space and be in orbit for about 5 10 15
20 minutes
see the curvature of the planet and
experience weightlessness before you
come back down to earth
but for students for ordinary people who
are not millionaires or billionaires
as of today it is very hard to become an
astronaut
but maybe in the next 20 years if india
does become ambitious
and start a human space flight program
to the moon to mars etc
then there could be good um
a good future for students who wish to
become
astronauts in which case there would be
a training program for astronauts etc
you would need to have certain uh a
certain kind of psychological profile
and certain physical attributes you need
to be fit
and all that and if you are able to go
through this rigorous program you may be
able to become
an astronaut but that is all currently
in the realm of fiction
as of today india india hasn't taken the
first step yet
the first human space flight still
hasn't taken place
so it's all in the future but i hope
that in the next 20 30 years
indian students will be able to have a
realistic ambition
of becoming astronauts and traveling
into space i hope it happens
okay one more question
if our character behavior physicality
all that took from the genes of our
parents or ancestors
does that mean that we are just that
accumulated or upgraded version of
physical intelligence with our own
self-consciousness
see we are a product of the genes of
our ancestors if you go back
ten generations you may have more than a
thousand ancestors it's not just one
lineage
we are a combination of multiple
lineages and if you go back a thousand
years
you may be a combination of several
thousand lineages
right so we are as we are the sum total
of the various attributes and
characteristics of our ancestors right
so that's what we have inherited and it
does determine to a great extent our
various uh physical
mental psychological properties right
how tall you're gonna be
how physically strong you're gonna be
how intelligent
or not you will be what sort of
appearance you have what's
your eye color hair color what's your
skin tone and whatnot all that right so
that all comes from your genes
from your genetics but there's something
that we learn as well there is nature
which is your genes and there is nurture
the kind of environment you grow up in
the kind of influences you are exposed
to in the kind of
things that you find an interest in so
if you study certain things or if you
have a certain kind of education you
are going to become uh maybe more
intelligent maybe more knowledgeable
etc if you if there are if you take two
twins
and you put them in two very different
environments they're going to become
very different people
so it's not just the genes it's also the
kind of environment
that you grow in so that's what
determines overall
the kind of life trajectory that a
person
will take
one more question will humans ever be
immortal
is what freyas asks well as of today
it's not possible to make humans
immortal there is there's a lot of
research being done in the west
in that direction uh how to reverse
aging etc
uh it's all about the telomeres so we
have human chromosomes and the ends of
the chromosomes are called
telomeres and it is found that as a
person ages these telomeres become
shorter and shorter
and that seems to be linked very
strongly with the process of
aging so if you can reverse the
shortening of the size of the telomeres
then the thing the the thinking goes
that you may be able to
either stop aging or even reverse it so
uh
research is being done in the direction
the other way to extend human life is to
replace organs so if you can well
acquire organs from somewhere
maybe go to china or if you could grow
organs synthetically
then you could replace a person's heart
lung livers
liver heart lungs liver kidneys spleen
even eyes skin whatnot right it may be
possible to do that
so that could extend the lifestyle
lifespan of a person maybe teeth as well
but what about the mind the brain and
that is the
real big big question can you extend the
mind
can you keep the brain functioning like
it used to function when you were
like let's say 20 years old is it
possible
so what one finds is that as you as you
acquire new memories the brain
actively forgets
memories that it deems to be unimportant
so as you progress in life over the
years and the decades you learn new
things you absorb more information new
information
but in that process the brain also
erases
certain information that it deems to be
not important
right so if a person were to live 100
years or 200 years
it's possible they may become a
completely different person because
all the old information is gone and they
have acquired new information
and it's also possible that the brain
may not be designed
to last that long defects may
come up in the brain alzheimer's disease
various plaques
parkinson's disease and whatnot right so
we don't know if it is possible to
extend the lifespan of the brain
and even if we are able to do that the
memories that are in the information
that's absorbed may turn you into a
completely different person
so these are the challenges that we face
in uh
in possibly becoming immortal so the
question is
is it even desirable to like to live
that long is it
a pleasurable experience just keep on
experiencing things
or is it going to have problems
is it going to cause problems mentally
emotionally psychologically etcetera
so we don't know that so i don't know if
it is actually desirable to
to be immortal that's that's the answer
all right let me take a couple of live
chat
questions
okay this is a interesting question by
dungar singh johan is it safe to create
a black hole
in a lab what are its negative and
positive aspects i think it's safe
enough to create a very small
microscopic black hole in a lab
because a microscopic black hole is so
small it's going to explode immediately
through hawking radiation
through the process of walking radiation
it is so small
and so hot that it will evaporate
explosively
almost instantaneously so when the large
hadron collider was
going to be turned on there was this
concern that
it would generate it would create
micro black holes in its collisions
and the calculations were done and it
was clearly shown that it would
pose no threat
to life on earth or to the planet itself
it would not pose any problem
so as long as we are creating micro
black holes
there is no real problem but if one were
to create a larger black hole
then it could possibly swallow up the
entire planet that is a possibility
but as of today we don't have the means
of doing that right we don't have the
means of doing that
so it is all theoretical uh as of today
it's not possible to create black holes
in the lab
one more question let me take one more
question
let me see give me a moment please
okay simpo asks why doesn't the moon
have gravity it does have gravity the
moon has gravity but its gravity is
much less than that of the earth the
mass of the moon is about 1
6 of that of the earth and therefore its
gravity is 1
6 of that of the earth so if you were to
if your weight is 60 kilos here on earth
if you go to the moon your weight is
going to be 10 kilos so there is gravity
but your
the gravity is much weaker it's
one-sixth that
of the earth so that is the deal
on the moon
okay let me take any other questions
akash asks what is a boltzmann brain a
both burn brain
is a it's a thought experiment it says
that it
is there is a very small probability
that the various atoms etc of the
universe could spontaneously combine to
create a fully functioning
human brain somewhere in the universe
there is a very small
non-zero probability that this could
spontaneously happen
it's it's almost impossible but it's
it's not
entirely impossible so such a brain that
would spontaneously
assemble itself on its own somewhere in
the universe
is what's called a boltzmann brain and
there are a number of thought
experiments that people have done with
this
all in the realm of the of the question
of what consciousness
is so that in very brief is what a
boltzmann brain is
it's an interesting topic maybe i could
discuss it in more detail
in a future episode
okay i think that's it for today it's
been
over 90 minutes thank you guys thank you
everybody
ladies gentlemen all of you for your
questions
i appreciate it very much thank you for
participating
and i will see you very soon in the next
episode i wish you a good day a good
night take care
bye